Ardella Tibby papers, 1941-1989
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ardella Tibby papers
1941-1989
2167
UCLA Library Special Collections
7.0 linear ft. (14 boxes)
Ardy Tibby is a lesbian feminist activist and organizer as well as an entertainer and author. Her collection focuses on her personal life and connections during her life in California and Phoenix, Arizona.
Tibby, Ardy 1941-
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access materials you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
Collection contains 8 reels of 1/4-inch audio tape.
Acquisition Information
Provenance unknown. This collection is part of an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW) and the UCLA Library.
Biography
Ardella Tibby was born on May 4, 1941. She became a teacher in the late 1960s and after coming out as a lesbian, joined the lesbian activist and cultural community. She began performing as a storyteller in festivals and community events, touring with artists such as Chocolate Waters throughout the 1980s and participating in the Califia community. She was a co-founder of the lesbian production group Delta Pi in 1984 which operated in Santa Rosa, California until 1989. She was the guest editor of Sinister Wisdom 80 entitled "Willing Up and Keeling Over: a Lesbian Handbook of Death Rights and Rituals." She has been and is currently involved with Older Lesbians Organizing for Change (OLOC), the Lesbian Archives and the Women's Circus. She resides with her partner Jean Taylor in Victoria, Australia. She refers to herself as a "proud, loud, bearded lesbian."
Scope and Content
This collection contains materials relating to the life and activities of Ardy Tibby. The bulk of the collection represents 1970-1985, a time when Tibby was heavily involved in lesbian community organizations as an organizer, storyteller and participant. A large part of the collections is made up of photographs, journals and scrapbook pages covering Tibby's early life. Also included is a correspondence between Tibby and various friends and colleagues. Although there are some aspects of the collection that deal with logistics of Tibby's touring schedule, the majority of the materials are personal and community oriented.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 7347949
Tibby, Ardy; Lesbian activists--California--Los Angeles--Archives.
Container List
- Memorabilia (Postcards)., 1980-1982.; postcards held together with a metal ring (Box 1, Folder 1)
  This box contains postcards from friends and lovers, mostly sent from travel destinations.
- Address books, diary., 1982.; two bound books (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Two bound books, one acted as an address book, the other is a daily calendar/diary that describes day to day activities and emotions.
- Memorabilia., 1982.; handwritten notes, printed paper, drawings, brochures (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This folder includes information about camping and music festivals. Includes correspondence between participants as well as promotional material for festivals.
- Memorabilia., 1983.; flyers, journals, handwritten notes/letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
  The bulk of this folder contains personal correspondence. Also included are flyers for feminist lesbian events and performers.
- Memorabilia., 1984.; postcards, bound diary, black and white photographs (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Contains memorabilia from 1984 including a bound daily diary kept by Ardy Tibby as well as photographs and some correspondence.
- Correspondence., 1984.; handwritten and typed paper held together by a metal ring (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Contains personal correspondence between Ardy Tibby and various friends.
- Storytelling., 1980-1989.; flyers, newspaper clippings (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Flyers for storytelling events featuring Ardy Tibby as well as newspaper clippings covering similar events.
- Address books, diaries., 1984.; one spiral, one library bound book (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Address books and daily diaries kept by Ardy Tibby.
- Correspondence., 1985.; postcards, handwritten and typewritten letters (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence (2)., 1985.; postcards, handwritten and typewritten letters (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Contains correspondence between Ardy Tibby and various friends.
- Photos., 1955-1972.; photographs (Box 4, Folder 1)
  This folder contains photographs of various sizes. Some color, some black and white and a number of them are mounted or otherwise framed. Most of the photographs depict vacations or celebrations.
- Calendars., 1962-1966.; spiral bound calendars (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Personal calendars for Ardy Tibby from 1962, 1962 and 1966.
- Calendars., 1968-1971.; spiral bound calendars (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Four calendars, all published by the Rand Corporation.
- Calendars., 1972-1975.; stapled and spiral bound calendars (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Three daily calendars for Ardy Tibby.
- Photos., 1960-1980 approximately.; photographs (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Photographs of various sizes and formats. Occasional description on the back of individual photographs but no overarching organization or thematic separation.
- Birth through junior high school., 1941-1955.; photographs, scrapbook pages, bound and typed manuscript (Box 5, Folder 1)
  This folder contains pages from a scrapbook featuring photographs with handwritten descriptions. Also contained are report cards from elementary school and essays written for school credit.
- High school and college 1/9., 1955-1962.; black and white photographs, handwritten notes (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Contains family photos as well as photos with Ardy Tibby and friends. Written materials are personal reflections.
- High school and college 2/9., 1955-1962.; cassette tape (Box 5, Folder 3)
  The label on the cassette tapes states "Side 1 File 1 Birth - 59GR" and "Side 2 File 1 JHS - young lesbian, repressed"
- High school and college 3/9., 1955-1962.; scrapbook pages, photographs (Box 5, Folder 4)
  This folder contains scrapbook pages featuring photographs of teachers and classmates with accompanying descriptions.
- High school and college 4/9., 1955-1962.; scrapbook pages, photographs (Box 5, Folder 5)
  This folder contains scrapbook pages featuring photographs accompanied by descriptions. Most of the photos are of classmates or teachers.
- High school and college 5/9., 1955-1962.; spiral bound calendar (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Spiral bound calendar with notes and activities described.
- High school and college 6/9., 1955-1962.; photographs (Box 5, Folder 7)
  This folder contains photographs of various sizes depicting Ardy Tibby and her sorority sisters from several events.
- High school and college 7/9., 1955-1962.; canvas (Box 5, Folder 8)
  Large piece of canvas with drawing on it, folded and in plastic.
- High school and college 8/9., 1955-1962.; handwritten notes (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Written materials including reflections and correspondence from Ardy Tibby's year spent in Spain.
- High school and college., 1955-1962.; printed calendars (Box 5, Folder 10)
  This folder contains two different calendars containing notes on activities.
- Memorabilia and photos., 1970.; photographs, carbon paper (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Teacher evaluations for Ardy Tibby as well as vacation photographs.
- Newspaper clippings., 1970-1980 approximately.; newsprint (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Clippings regarding sports teams and miscellaneous items of interest. Clippings are removed from their original publications, so dates and sources are not available.
- Personal materials., 1951-1967.; bound books, passport and plastic chips (Box 6, Folder 1)
  This folder contains miscellaneous personal materials including identification, Alcoholics Anonymous sobriety chips, autograph books from elementary school and a daily diary from tenth grade.
- Flyers and brochures., No date.; printed paper (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Flyers and brochures for various feminist lesbian events, gathering and services.
- Correspondence., 1973-1976.; handwritten paper, greeting cards (Box 6, Folder 3)
  This folder contains correspondence with a number of Ardy Tibby's friends and lovers.
- Year in Spain., 1976.; handwritten paper, spiral bound notebook (Box 6, Folder 4)
  This folder includes correspondence, diaries, calendars and hostel information from Ardy Tibby's travels to Spain.
- Miscellaneous., No date.; handwritten notes (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Postcards and handwritten notes.
- Drawings., No Date.; pencil drawings (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Pencil drawings of Ardy Tibby, unattributed.
- Photographs., 1969-1970.; photographs, newspaper clippings, handwritten notes (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Original label states "Summer 1969-Summer 1970 USA + Canada Trip Jimmy's 16th Birthday, Mom + Jim's New House, Yucca Valley CAlifornia, Aunt Mattie Napa California - Book #4."
- Photographs., 1975.; photographs (Box 7, Folder 3)
  Photographs of Ardy Tibby and friends.
- Photographs., 1981-1983.; photographs (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Photographs., 1979-1980.; photographs (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Photographs., 1980-1985.; photographs (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Flyers and brochures., 1970-1980.; printed paper, photocopies (Box 8, Folder 1)
  Flyers and brochures for various lesbian and women's events including readings, concerts and meetings. Some of the flyers are advertising storytelling and/or appearances of Ardy Tibby.
- Woman rising., 1977.; bound printed, photocopies (Box 8, Folder 2)
  Includes four issues of Woman Rising, a women's periodical. Volume II No. 6 Nov-Dec 1977 Phoeniz, AZ Volume II No. 5 Sept-Oct 1977 Phoenix, AZ Volume II No. 4 July - August 1977 Phoenix, AZ Volume II No. 3 May - June 1977 Phoenix, AZ
- Newspaper clippings., 1977-1980.; newsprint (Box 8, Folder 3)
  Contains newspaper clippings collected by Ardy Tibby.
- Lesbian tide., 1977.; newsprint (Box 8, Folder 4)
  Contains two issues of The Lesbian Tide: A Feminist Lesbian Publication, written by and for the Rising Tide of Women Today September/October 1977 November/December 1977 Also includes a photocopy and a few clippings.
- Correspondence., 1978.; handwritten letters, typed letters (Box 8, Folder 5)
  Correspondence between Ardy Tibby and various friends and colleagues.
- Newsletters., 1979.; printed, bound newsletters (Box 8, Folder 6)
  Contains newsletters from various organizations including Demeter, the Lesbian Herstory Archives and Lesbian Connection.
- Collected writings., 1977-1980.; printed paper, photocopies, carbon copies (Box 8, Folder 7)
  Writings collected by Ardy Tibby including: A Radical Feminist's Response to Liberal Feminism by Mia Albright The Bearded Woman's Exchange Country Western Fluff by Jean Johnson The Sweet Sting of Success by Rita Mae Brown from Mother Jones A Glance at Oral Communication in the Lesbian Feminist Counter Culture by Sandra M. Anthony The Day American Turned into Woman by Mia Albright In the Image of Woman by Mia Albright
- Festival materials., 1980-1981.; printed paper, photocopies, brochures (Box 8, Folder 8)
  Brochures, flyers, schedules and itineraries for various women's and lesbian festivals and pride events.
- Lavender morning., 1980-1981.; printed and stapled paper (Box 8, Folder 9)
  Contains issues of Lavender Morning (for Lesbians) Vol. 2 Issue 1 Vol. 2 Issue 2 Vol. 1 Number 1 Vol. 1 Number 2 Vol. 1 Number 3 Vol. 1 Number 4 Vol. 1 Number 5
- Womoon change - pacific coast tour., 1981.; flyers, handwritten notes, receipts, checks (Box 8, Folder 10)
  Includes correspondence, set lists, financial documentation and flyers for the Womoon Change tour featuring Ardy Tibby as a storyteller.
- Correspondence., 1979.; handwritten letters, photos (Box 9, Folder 1)
  Correspondence between Ardy Tibby and her friends and colleagues. Includes some memorabilia including paper dolls and handmade photo frames.
- Correspondence., 1980.; handwritten letters (Box 9, Folder 2)
  Correspondence between Ardy Tibby and her friends and colleagues. Also includes some hand drawings and some postcards.
- Correspondence., 1981.; handwritten letters (Box 9, Folder 3)
  Correspondence between Ardy Tibby and her friends and colleagues. Also includes handmade calendars.
- Photographs., 1977-1978.; photographs, polaroids (Box 10, Folder 1)
  Photographs from vacation in Pismo Beach with Ardy Tibby and friends.
- Photographs., 1964-1966.; photographs (Box 10, Folder 2)
  Both black and white and color photographs.
- Photographs., 1975-1982.; photographs (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Majority of the photographs in this folder are polaroids, but are also mixed in with other photographic formats.
- Ephemera., 1970-1980.; various clothing items, books and ephemera (Box 11)
  Inventory – Ardy Tibby Box 11 T-Shirts Helaine Victoria Press Shirty made for Ardy Tibby by Caryl DeGroot Tribad Productions in Sonoma County shirt with air brushed portrait of Ardy Tibby made by Therese Bur Waikiki shirt shirt made by Amelia Glaser by Ardy Tibby Miscellaneous Cap with drawing by Catherine Clinger during a dyke gathering at Magnolia Acres (locally known as La Punta) Quilt made for Ardy Tibby by Dyke Witch and priestess Ffiona Morgan 1988 Logo for Delta pi, lesbian production company made out of stained glass Punky Brewster converse shoes Rolodex Contents – Note on the bag "Probably 95% of these are Lesbians. These were in my rollodex over an almost 10 year open ending in January 93" Guest book from Ardy's Guest Room of Home/Dyke Center in Santa Rosa, CA "Not everyone signed it, but its a nice something. The household functioned as a dyke space from Nov 1988-April 1944." Books Breast Cartoons by Yvonne Eldresse - signed by artist and given to Ardy Tibby 1988 Graphic Details by Bev Balliett and Patti Patton 1979 – includes photo of Ardy Tibby – signed by authors and given to Ardy Tibby Take me Like a Photograph: Writings by Chocolate Waters 1977 signed by author and given to Ardy Tibby A Scrap of Royal Need by Mia Albright 1980 Womyn/Friends a Book of Poems by Jean Sirius signed by author and given to Ardy Tibby 1979
- Midwest lesbian express tour with Chocolate Waters., 1980.; postcards, photographs, handwritten notes and printed flyers (Box 12, Folder 1)
  Flyers, correspondence, financial information, contact information and promotional material for the Midwest Lesbian Express Tour featuring Ardy Tibby and Chocolate Waters.
- Resources., No Date.; printed paper, photocopies (Box 12, Folder 2)
  Contact information for the Califia community as well as printed community resources.
- Miscellaneous., No Date.; printed paper, hand drawings (Box 12, Folder 3)
  Miscellaneous materials including paper olls, ahnd drawings, printed paper and handwritten notes.
- Periodicals., 1984-1993.; published books and periodicals (Box 13)
  Container list contained in box: Sinister Wisdom Issues 36, 38, 39, 45, 47; Common Lives, Lesbian Lives Issues 12, 14, 27, 32, 34, 35, 37, 39, 46; Conditions Issues 11/12 and 16; The Lesbian Issue: Essays from Signs, 1985.
- Audio reel: Ardy Tibby in Sacramento at Lioness Bookstore., 1988. (Box 14)
- Audio reel: Judy Freespirit in Sacramento at Lioness Bookstore., 1988. (Box 14)
- Audio reel: Ardy Tibby in San Francisco., 1988. (Box 14)
- Audio reel: Judy Freespirit in San Francisco., 1988. (Box 14)
- Audio reel: Ardy Tibby in Santa Cruz., 1988. (Box 14)
- Audio reel: Judy Freespirit in Santa Cruz., 1988. (Box 14)
- Audio reel: Ardy Tibby at Clairelight Bookstore Santa Rosa., 1988. (Box 14)
- Audio reel: Ardy Tibby and Judy Freespirit at Clairelight Bookstore Santa Rosa., 1988. (Box 14)